BU Records: Movement for the Perpetuation of Baylor University, Inclusive: 1928, undated, Bulk: 1928 April-June, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: Movement for the Perpetuation of Baylor University
Inclusive: 1928, undated, Bulk: 1928 April-June, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/122
Movement for the Perpetuation of Baylor University
1 document box.
The BU Records: Movement for the Perpetuation of Baylor University consist of correspondence, literary manuscripts, financial documents, and newspaper clippings concerning the proposed move of Baylor to Dallas and efforts to keep the university in Waco.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
In 1927 November, members of the Baptist General Convention of Texas (BGCT) created the Education Commission, whose role was to offer suggestions for improving Baptist denominational schools in Texas. Within a few months, the Commission voted to recommend that Baylor University be relocated to Dallas, and planned to formally make their recommendation during a special session of the BGCT scheduled for 1928 June 5. The proposal for the university’s removal came about because some Dallas citizens offered 1,000 acres of land and $1,500,000 to the institution if the school was moved.
Shortly after learning that the Education Commission planned to suggest that Baylor be moved to Dallas, many Wacoans and Baylor alumni began expressing their disapproval of the idea. In an early effort to frustrate the proposed move, the Waco Chamber of Commerce offered to provide the university with three new buildings: a chapel (to be named Waco Hall); a women's dormitory; and a new athletic stadium. On 1928 May 1, in hopes of persuading the Education Commission to reverse their decision about the removal of Baylor to Dallas, members of the Waco Chamber of Commerce and other interested individuals launched the Movement for the Perpetuation of Baylor University. This program, part of the larger Greater Baylor Campaign, was designed to disseminate information regarding the disadvantages of moving Baylor to Dallas and offer reasons for why the school should remain in Waco.
Within a few weeks of the creation of the Movement for the Perpetuation of Baylor University, the Education Commission decided not to recommend the relocation of Baylor on the conditions that Wacoans raise $1,000,000 within the next seven years, of which $350,000 had to be pledged by June 5 to build Waco Hall, and that Texas Baptists raise another $1,000,000 within the same timeframe. With slightly over one week to raise $350,000, individuals involved in the Movement organized committees and sent people all over the city to seek donations. When the BGCT met on June 5, the Movement had received pledges from Waco citizens totaling $416,350. Consequently, the Education Commission unanimously recommended that Baylor remain in Waco.
Scope and Content
The BU Records: Movement for the Perpetuation of Baylor University begins in 1928 April and ends in 1928 November. Correspondence, the largest series in the collection, consists of letters concerning the Movement for the Perpetuation of Baylor University and efforts to keep Baylor in Waco. The collection also contains literary manuscripts and newspaper clippings, as well as two receipts.
Arrangement
No finding aid existed for the BU Records: Movement for the Perpetuation of Baylor University prior to the creation of this one. Initially, the few literary manuscripts and financial documents were interspersed among the correspondence. While the literary productions and financial documents have since been placed in their own separate series, the original order of the correspondence has been preserved.
Currently, the records of the Movement for the Perpetuation of Baylor University are arranged in four series: I. Correspondence, II. Literary Productions, III. Financial Documents, and IV. Newspaper Clippings.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/122. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Items in related collections
BU Records: Greater Baylor Campaign, Inclusive: 1927-1932, Bulk: 1930-1932
Related references
“Actual Building Will Begin After June 5 Believes Dr. Johnson.” Daily Lariat (Waco, TX), 1928 May 24.
“Convention is With Waco.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1928 June 8.
“Dallas C. — C. Will Reply to Wacoans’ Request May 12.” Daily Lariat (Waco, TX), 1928 May 5.
Daniel, M. P., Jr. “Dallas Offers 1, 1-2 Million; Waco to Fight.” Daily Lariat (Waco, TX), 1928 April 19.
“Dr. Brooks Discusses Relocation Rumors.” Daily Lariat (Waco, TX), 1928 January 4.
“Jubilee Convention Will Meet at First Baptist Church Today.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1928 June 5.
“Special Convention to be in Waco June 5.” Daily Lariat (Waco, TX), 1928 May 12.
“Waco Chamber of Commerce Begins New Fight to Hold Baylor.” Daily Lariat (Waco, TX), 1928 May 2.
“Waco Raises $416,350.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1928 June 5.
“Waco’s Drive for $350,000 for Baylor Will Start Monday.” Daily Lariat (Waco, TX), 1928 May 25.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baptist General Convention of Texas -- History.; Baylor University -- Alumni and alumnae.; Baylor University -- History -- 20th century.
Places
Waco Hall (Baylor University).
Subjects
Baptist associations -- Texas -- Waco -- History.; Baptists -- Texas -- History.; Fund raising -- Texas.; Universities and colleges -- Texas -- Waco -- Planning.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Financial records.
- Correspondence, 1928 April-June, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains correspondence regarding efforts to keep Baylor University in Waco.
  - Campaign Correspondence (1 of 3), 1928 April-June, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Campaign Correspondence (2 of 3), 1928 April-June, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Campaign Correspondence (3 of 3), 1928 April-June, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Literary Productions, 1928 May, undated; 2
  This series contains literary manuscripts regarding efforts to keep Baylor University in Waco.
  - Minutes, Notes, Publicity Lists, 1928 May, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Financial Documents, 1928 May, undated; 3
  This series contains two receipts.
  - Receipts, 1928 May, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1928 April-June, undated; 4
  This series contains newspaper clippings from Waco, Dallas, and Houston newspapers concerning the proposed move of Baylor University to Dallas.
  - Waco, Dallas, and Houston Newspapers, 1928 April-June (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Waco Newspapers, 1928 April-May, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)